<document>
<properties>
  <title>Dalma Archive (.dar)</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="What is a .dar file?">
  <p>
    Dalmacon uses a jar file that has the <tt>.dar</tt> extension to package a workflow application (which possibly consists of multiple class files and jar files) into a single file. This makes it easy to copy/install workflow applications into Dalmacon. A dar file has the following structure:
  </p>
<pre><![CDATA[
foo.dar
  +- META-INF
  |   +- MANIFEST.MF
  +- *.jar
  +- org
  |   +- acme
  |       +- Foo.class
  |       +- ...
  ...
]]></pre>
  <subsection name="MANIFEST.MF">
    <p>
      <tt>MANIFEST.MF</tt> is used in the same way and has the same format as in a jar file. Dalma adds one optiona attribute called <tt>Dalma-Main-Class</tt>, which points to the fully-qualified class name of a <a href="../dalma-container/apidocs/index.html?dalma/Program.html">Program</a>-derived class that serves as the entry point of a workflow application. (It's analogous to the <tt>Main-Class</tt> attribute that points to a class that has the <tt>main</tt> method.)
    </p><p>
      When this attribute is not present, <tt>Main</tt> (a class in the root package) is used.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="*.jar">
    <p>
      Additional jar files that a workflow application depends on may simply be placed at the top-level. Those jar files are made available to the workflow application classloader.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Class files">
    <p>
      Class files can be put into a dar file just like in a jar file, and those class files are also made available to the same workflow application classloader that loads <tt>*.jar</tt>. (Alternatively, you can choose to package all your code into jar files and have no bare-naked <tt>*.class</tt> files.)
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Working with dar files">
  <subsection name="When to use a dar file?">
    <p>
      Use a dar file when you distribute your workflow application.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="When NOT to use a dar file?">
    <p>
      When you are developing a workflow application, use the "exploded" format (which is a normal directory that has the same file structure as a dar file) to improve the speed of the debug cycle. Creating and extracting a dar file is unnecessary overhead in such a situation.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="How to create a dar file?">
    <p>
      With Maven, install <a href="../maven-dalma-plugin/">Maven dalma plugin</a> and use <a href="../maven-dalma-plugin/goals.html">dalma:dar</a> target.
    </p><p>
      With Ant, simply use <a href="http://ant.apache.org/manual/CoreTasks/jar.html">the jar task</a> like this.
    </p>
<source><![CDATA[
<jar jarfile="build/my.dar">
  <manifest>
    <attribute name="Dalma-Main-Class" value="org.acme.Foo" />
  </manifest>
  <fileset dir="build/classes" />
  <fileset dir="lib" includes="*.jar" />
</jar>
]]></source>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body></document>