<document>
<properties>
  <title>Embedding Dalma Engine</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Create workflow engine">
  <p>
    The next thing we'll do is to set up a workflow engine. First, we create a new <tt>Engine</tt> instance like this:
  </p>
<source>
Engine engine = EngineFactory.newEngine("foo.workflow.");
</source>
  <p>
    <tt>Engine</tt> object represents a running workflow engine instance. It creates "./dalma" directory and uses it to persist the state of the running "conversations", which are the programs running inside the engine. If you already have persisted conversations in this directory (for example you've stopped the VM while running conversations and restarted it later), then those conversations will be automatically picked up by the new engine instance.
  </p>
  <p>
    The parameter "foo.workflow." indicates the package name that we'll be using to write conversations. To transparently suspend and persist running conversations, Dalma relies on bytecode instrumentation (<a href="instrumentation.html">more details</a>.) For now, we'll isolate the conversation code into one package and use runtime instrumentation.
  </p>
  <p>
    This instantiation is the simplest possible way you can construct an engine. If you need more control, check <a href="apidocs/index.html?dalma/EngineFactory.html">EngineFactory documentation</a>.
  </p>
</section>
<section name="Set up endpoints">
  <p>
    Next, we'll add endpoints to an engine, like this:
  </p>
<source>
EmailEndPoint eep = (EmailEndPoint)engine.addEndPoint(
  "endPoint1","smtp://hangman@kohsuke.org!pop3://username:password@mail.kohsuke.org");
</source>
  <p>
    The first parameter is the name of a newly added endpoint. Endpoints are identified by their name inside an engine. Persisted conversations use names to connect back to endpoints when they are resumed.
  </p><p>
    The second parameter is an endpoint URL (<a href="endpoint.html#Endpoint_URL">more info</a>) that captures the configuration of an endpoint in one string. This somewhat ugly string is convenient because in most cases endpoint configurations are highly environment-dependent and therefore you don't want to hard-code them in your program.
  </p><p>
    You can also choose to create endpoints programatically, or you can use Spring, Groovy, and etc to configure endpoints. See <a href="configure.html">this document</a> for more details.
  </p><p>
    For e-mail endpoint, we need one more configuration; we need to tell it what we want to do when the endpoint sees a new incoming e-mail that is not related to any of the running conversations. We do this by the following code. We'll fill this part later:
  </p>
<source>
eep.setNewMailHandler(new NewMailHandler() {
  public void onNewMail(MimeMessage mail) {
    ;
  }
});
</source>
</section>
<section name="Start engine">
  <p>
    We are done with the configuration, so let's start the engine.
  </p>
<source>
engine.start();
</source>
  <p>
    Engine doesn't run and endpoints won't accept incoming messages until you invoke the <tt>start</tt> method. This prevents the synchronization problem --- you don't want a part of the engine to start accepting incoming messages before you prepare the other part of the engine.
  </p><p>
    Engine runs asynchronously by using other threads, so this method call returns immediately. The main thread can do anything it wants at this point, but in this tutorial I just let the main thread exit by returning from the main method. Since engine has its own thread, the JVM will keep running in this way (if you really wanted to shut down the JVM, you can invoke <tt>Engine.stop()</tt> method.
  </p>
</section>
</body>
</document>