<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Hangman sample</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Overview">
      <p>
        Dalma engine ships with the hangman example that implements <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hangman">the hangman game</a> by using <a href="dalma-endpoint-email/">the e-mail endpoint</a>.
      </p>
      <subsection name="How to run">
        <p>
          First, build the sample as follows. This will compile the sample into a jar file.
        </p>
<source>
$ cd /paht/to/the/distribution/dir
$ cd samples/hangman
$ ant
</source>
        <p>
          To run this sample, type the following command:
        </p>
<source>
$ java -jar target/hangman.jar &lt;email endpointURL>
</source>
        <p>
          The <i>&lt;email endpointURL></i> specifies how the program connects to the mail server. It can be something like <tt>"smtp://hangman@kohsuke.org!pop3://userid:password@mail.kohsuke.org/"</tt>. See <a href="dalma-endpoint-email/endpointURL.html">this document for details</a>
        </p>
        <p>
          If started successfully, you'll see the following message:
        </p>
        <source>engine started and ready for action</source>
        <p>
        	Now you can write an e-mail to the e-mail address you specified in the above endpoint URL, and it will start a new hangman game. When the e-mail is received by the program, you'll see the following message:
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[Starting a new game for Kohsuke Kawaguchi <kohsuke.kawaguchi@sun.com>]]></source>
        <p>
          And the program sends a reply e-mail like this:
        </p>
<source>
Word: _ _ _ _

You Chose: __________________________

6 more guesses
</source>
        <p>
          Pick a character from A to Z by replying to this e-mail, like this:
        </p>
<source>
hangman@kohsuke.org wrote:
> Word: _ _ _ _
> 
> You Chose: __________________________
> 
> 6 more guesses
> 
> 

x

-- 
Kohsuke Kawaguchi
Sun Microsystems                   kohsuke.kawaguchi@sun.com
</source>
        <p>
          When this e-mail gets delivered to the program, it prints out the following line, and sends back a reply. Repeat this process until you find the correct answer, or you run out of your chances.
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[Received a reply from Kohsuke Kawaguchi <kohsuke.kawaguchi@sun.com>]]></source>
        <p>
          The conversation logic is implemented in the <a href="/source/browse/dalma/dalma/samples/hangman/src/java/dalma/sample/hangman/HangmanWorkflow.java?view=markup"><tt>HangmanWorkflow</tt></a> class, and it should be straight-forward to follow.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="More about this game">
        <p>
          This sample can handle multiple concurrent hangman games very naturally --- there will be one instance of <tt>HangmanWorkflow</tt> for one on-going game. Send mutliple e-mails to the program from a single e-mail address, and you can see that they create different Hangman games.
        </p><p>
          The other experiment you should do is to kill the program and restart it. Dalma persists the state of on-going conversations, so information about the on-going hangman games will survive the VM shutdown.
        </p>
        <p>
          You can browse <a href="/source/browse/dalma/dalma/samples/hangman/src/java/dalma/sample/hangman/">the complete source code online</a>.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="But I don't have a mail account I can play with!">
        <p>
          I deployed this sample at <tt>hangman at kohsuke dot org</tt>, so you can write to this e-mail address and play the hangman game. To make it interesting, this program shuts down every half an hour and restarted half an hour later.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>